<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mathematics on Eric Peña</title>
    <link>https://ericpena.github.io/categories/mathematics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mathematics on Eric Peña</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ericpena.github.io/categories/mathematics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Speed Walking in Chicago</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/speed-walking/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/speed-walking/</guid>
      <description>Chicagoans Always Speed My morning commute to work in the heart of downtown Chicago is very regular: Enjoy blazing hot coffee and listen to an interesting podcast all while super-speed-walking all the way to the office. I often think how much time I would save by teleporting to the office instead. Even while often walking faster than most on the busy morning sidewalks, there are folks that zoom past me but still appear to be walking gracefully.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Tensors</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/tensors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/tensors/</guid>
      <description>Motivation:
 General Relativity Inertia Tensor Stress Tensor  It took me a whole week figure out what a tensor actually is. You will find many definitions and some are only partially correct. Let&amp;rsquo;s walk through the different explanations and learn how to think about them.
 (Array Definition) Tensor = Multi-dimensional array of numbers (scalars (rank 0), vectors (rank 1), matricies (rank 2), etc.). This is true in a sense but there is a truer geometrical meaning behind the concept of a tensor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mathematics of Network Theory</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2018/network-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2018/network-theory/</guid>
      <description>Graphs may be represented in the form of a matrix. Main types of graphs that may be represented are:
 Simple Graph Multigraph Directed Graph Weighted Graph Bipartite Graph  Directed Graph Directed graphs are graphs that contain edges with direction. Vertices may have inward and outward edges.
Unlike adjacency matricies for simped graphs, adjacency matricies for directed graphs are non-symmetric. Elements of an adjacency matrix for a directed graph may be denoted as: $$A_{ij}$$ which represents an edge from vertex $j$ to $i$.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>