<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Complex Systems on Eric Peña</title>
    <link>https://ericpena.github.io/categories/complex-systems/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Complex Systems on Eric Peña</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ericpena.github.io/categories/complex-systems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>First Genetic Algorithm — Prints: ericpena</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/ga-intro/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/ga-intro/</guid>
      <description>Components of a Genetic Algorithm: The Genetic Algorithm Code Written in Python: from fuzzywuzzy import fuzz import random import string class Agent: def __init__(self, length): # Initialize a new agent self.string = &#39;&#39;.join(random.choice(string.ascii_letters) for _ in range(length)) self.fitness = -1 def __str__(self): return &#39;String: &#39; + str(self.string) + &#39; Fitness: &#39; + str(self.fitness) in_str = None in_str_len = None population = 20 generations = 5000 # All the code to evolve def ga(): agents = init_agents(population, in_str_len) for generation in range(generations): print(&#39;Generation: &#39; + str(generation)) agents = fitness(agents) agents = selection(agents) agents = crossover(agents) agents = mutation(agents) if any(agent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complexity — A Guided Tour Reflection</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/complexity-reflection-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/complexity-reflection-1/</guid>
      <description>Part I: Providing the multifaceted story of how complex systems has evolved into what it is today is no easy feat. Dr. Melanie Mitchell not only gives a comprehensive historical tour of science and mathematics, she also provides foundational knowledge that any reader can carry to appreciate the essence of what it means for a system to be complex in the technical sense. Early on, she gives a clear definition of complex systems as an interdisciplinary field that studies how large networks of entities with no central controller can organize themselves and exhibit collective behavior given simple rules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Complex Systems News Resources</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/news/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/news/</guid>
      <description>Keeping Up With Complex Systems Science News It can be difficult to find time to keep up with interesting science, especially when articles are dense and abstruse. With an unfortunate name like complex systems, keeping up with the intersting news can be a daunting task. Here are a few resources that I use to keep up with the fascinating world of complex systems and systems engineering.
 Santa Fe Institute  Sante Fe Institute Complexity Explorer  Quanta Magazine</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>