<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>musings - Eric Peña</title>
    <link>//ericpena.github.io/musings/index.xml</link>
    <description></description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="//ericpena.github.io/musings/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Birthday Everyday</title>
      <link>//ericpena.github.io/musings/birthday.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//ericpena.github.io/musings/birthday.html</guid>
      <description>Motivation Consider this scene from a Seinfeld episode (LINK if you&amp;rsquo;d like to watch the short clip)
Coworker: &amp;ldquo;Elaine? Cake?&amp;rdquo;
Elaine: &amp;ldquo;Oh, no thanks&amp;rdquo;
Coworker: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s Walter&amp;rsquo;s special day!&amp;rdquo;
Elaine: &amp;ldquo;You know, there&amp;rsquo;s 200 people who work in this office. Everyday is somebody&amp;rsquo;s special day.&amp;rdquo;
Firstly, if by &amp;ldquo;special day&amp;rdquo; she means birthdays, then this of course cannot be true since there are 365-ish days in a year and only 200 people who work in the office.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mismatched Socks</title>
      <link>//ericpena.github.io/musings/unmatching-socks.html</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//ericpena.github.io/musings/unmatching-socks.html</guid>
      <description>Introduction Probability pops up everywhere! One day, I was digging in a basket of (clean) clothes in search of socks pulling several of them out one by one. However, I pulled six socks out but none of them matched! I thought to myself: what the heck is the probability of THAT happening? So let&amp;rsquo;s dig into how one might figure this out. But before we start answering this, let&amp;rsquo;s be more clear about what the situation is.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Logistic Growth Model</title>
      <link>//ericpena.github.io/musings/logistic_growth.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//ericpena.github.io/musings/logistic_growth.html</guid>
      <description>Logistic Growth Model The simple difference equation below will show exponential growth behavior:
$$x_t = a x_{t-1}$$
However, it is often the case that a population cannot grow indefinitely but rather reach a population limit. This limit is called the population&amp;rsquo;s carrying capacity. To create a model with exponential growth but also incorporate this convergence to a population maximum limit, we may start with the following train of thought:
$$x_t = f(x_{t-1}) x_{t-1}$$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Logistic Map</title>
      <link>//ericpena.github.io/musings/logistic_map.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Mar 2020 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//ericpena.github.io/musings/logistic_map.html</guid>
      <description>Logistic Map The famous logistic map is a recurrence relation or polynomial mapping of degree 2. It is a nonlinear difference equation capable of capturing complex nonlinear dynamical behavior including chaos. This map was popularized by the biologist Robert May in a Nature article written in 1976. Sadly, Robert May has passed away recently on April 28, 2020. The equation is as follows:
$$x_{n+1} = r x_n (1 - x_n)$$</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Trajectory Angle</title>
      <link>//ericpena.github.io/musings/falling_balls.html</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//ericpena.github.io/musings/falling_balls.html</guid>
      <description>Introduction I had the pleasure of teaching physics for the Pre First-Year Academic and Career Engagement (PREFACE) Program. These are students that graduated high school and are transitioning into college to study engineering. The following is a problem I gave my students as a challenge question on their final. Many students found this problem interesting and we had a long discussion about the power of learning theoretical mechanics for the future of their respective degrees.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>