<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on ERIC PEÑA</title>
        <link>https://ericpena.github.io/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on ERIC PEÑA</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://ericpena.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Create Smarter Goals</title>
            <link>https://ericpena.github.io/posts/goals/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/posts/goals/</guid>
            <description>If you are anything like me, passion and self-motivation compels you to generate ambitious goals. I sometimes even write them down and share them with friends and family. Then, I sit back and contentedly coddle myself in satisfaction for merely creating this goal hoping it will provide direction and purpose. I do this all while holding onto the illusion that I am responsibly evaluating my needs and assessing my possible futures.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[

<p>If you are anything like me, passion and self-motivation compels you to generate ambitious goals. I sometimes even write them down and share them with friends and family. Then, I sit back and contentedly coddle myself in satisfaction for merely creating this goal hoping it will provide direction and purpose. I do this all while holding onto the illusion that I am responsibly evaluating my needs and assessing my possible futures. But when the time comes to initiate progress <a href="http://www.dictionary.com/e/word-fact-toward-vs-towards/">toward</a> my beautifully crafted goal, I have no clue how to begin. The once lustrous goal that sat so securely on the pedestal of inspiration and vision quickly vanishes into nothing. And the void is quickly filled with another goal that may or may not be reasonable but is still just as creative and ill-planned as the previous one. What better way to enjoy the thrills of self-guilt and rationalization? I have lived this viscous cycle for years. Some goals see the finish-line but most fall short, wither and die without a chance of revival. I read an <a href="https://www.inc.com/marcel-schwantes/science-says-92-percent-of-people-dont-achieve-goals-heres-how-the-other-8-perce.html">article</a> that claims that 92% of people never actually accomplish New Year’s goals they set out for themselves. I’m not comforted for sharing this struggle but I am disturbed that most people stray from their own agendas. This is my personal attempt to stay focused.</p>

<p>As with any bad habit, it takes awareness and a change of mind before it can be overcome. Displeased with my pile of unfinished projects, I decided to keep this idea on the forefront of my mind with the hopes that some brainstorming will do me some good.</p>

<blockquote>
<p>When in doubt, relentlessly obsess until an illuminating idea eventually dawns on you, eventually.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I soon realized that the heart of the issue is not the process used to accomplish a goal. Intrinsically, the problem is with the creation of the goal itself. When we have a goal already set for us, we tend to scurry around searching for the first step. We race to the finish-line without considering what we’re really aiming for or how it relates to everything else that’s important to us. I would argue that the problem that is halting execution is the misguided construction of the goal itself. What I propose is instead of racking your brain on <strong>how</strong> to accomplish goals, invest more time thinking about the goals themselves and how you defined them at the start.</p>

<p>Making challenging and achievable goals that are aligned with who you are and what you want in life will only focus your journey. I’m convinced that if you take the time to go through this process, you’ll be able to differentiate between empty hopes and meaningful, tangible ambitions. This will help connect your short-term and long-term goals making you feel like an actual productive human being.</p>

<p>Going through this process of insightful goal creation helps in the execution of the goal. A problem I often face is learning how to initiate and maintain rhythm. If what you’re trying to accomplish is well-defined and realistic, it lends itself to effective planning. The goal should be easy to break down into individual, manageable components. That way, the tasks you lay out for yourself won’t be daunting but rather exciting.</p>

<p>I have come up with two main considerations when it comes to creating goals:</p>

<ol>
<li>Goals should be well-defined, specific, and actionable</li>
<li>We should be organized and realistic about what you are willing to do</li>
</ol>

<p>The sections below go deeper into these two considerations.</p>

<h2 id="1-is-it-even-a-goal">1. Is it even a “goal”?</h2>

<p>Defining a goal the right way is crucial for assuring success. If a goal is too broad or complex, it&rsquo;s more of an idea than a goal. It gives you vision and motivation but isn’t helpful in learning how to begin. For example, if I had the goal:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Become a better writer</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>I would have no idea where to even start. This isn’t specific enough – I simply want to be a better writer without knowing how to actually be one. It’s a vague end-point and gives no information on what I need to accomplish. If instead my goals were:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Write 3 articles a month</strong></li>
<li><strong>Get feedback from friends</strong></li>
<li><strong>Read an article a day for input and inspiration</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>I immediately know where to begin. I started with a stretch goal and found a way of dividing it into individual components that are specific, manageable tasks. With a clear path in mind, this will motivate me to get started. It also has the same destination of “becoming a better writer” without the elusive daydreaming. And if the goal is still too broad, rinse and repeat.</p>

<h2 id="2-avoid-swimming-in-a-sea-of-goals-be-organized">2. Avoid swimming in a sea of goals – Be organized</h2>

<p>One important realization to keep on your side is that no matter how unfortunate the reality, we simply do not have time for everything. If you overwhelm yourself with too many goals, you are guaranteed little to no progress. This very issue ranks high on the lengthy list of obstacles I create for myself. The fear of spending time on one project coming at the expense of another consumes me and I rarely ever know what to spend time on. This seldom leads to quality output. Try to void distracting yourself from what you know is truly worth your time. Your <em>precious</em> time.</p>

<p>One method you can try is from Angela Duckworth’s <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Grit-Passion-Perseverance-Angela-Duckworth/dp/1501111108">Grit: The Power of Passion and Perseverance</a>. She writes about a conversation between Warren Buffet and his pilot about organizing goals. Here is the 3-step process:</p>

<ol>
<li>Write down a list of 25 career goals.</li>
<li>Do some soul searching and circle the five highest priority goals.</li>
<li>Take a hard look at the 20 goals you didn’t circle; avoid these at all cost. These are distractions that eat away time and energy from the goals that really matter.</li>
</ol>

<p>Try this exercise and see where it leads you. As you organize your goals, be honest and ask yourself: Is everything on here important to me? Are there even enough hours in a day? Is this the most impactful way to spend my time?</p>

<p>Although I have been thinking about my personal growth, motivation, and habits for what seems like most of my life, I am still developing a reliable effective process for tackling big goals. Hopefully thinking about goal creation in this way will give me a better chance. Over the years, I have landed on an overarching bit of learning – it’s not important to know where to start so long as you do. There isn’t enough time in life, let alone in a day – there is no use in wasting it. The learning that emerges about yourself and how you prioritize may surprise you. Now go craft your success.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
