<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Eric Peña</title>
    <link>https://ericpena.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Eric Peña</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ericpena.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Complex Systems News Resources</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/news/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/news/</guid>
      <description> Keeping Up With Complex Systems Science News It can be difficult to find time to keep up with interesting science, especially when articles are dense and abstruse. With an unfortunate name like complex systems, keeping up with the intersting news can be a daunting task.
 Santa Fe Institute Santa Fe Institute&amp;hellip;
 Sante Fe Institute Complexity Explorer Complexity Explorer&amp;hellip;
 Quanta Magazine Quanta&amp;hellip;

Nature Nature&amp;hellip;
 Quanta Magazine  Quanta Magazine  Quanta Magazine  OTHER FUN SCIENCE RESOURCES Quanta Magazine  Quanta Magazine  Quanta Magazine  Quanta Magazine </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adding Favicons</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/hugo-favicon/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/hugo-favicon/</guid>
      <description>Nothing makes a website look polished like a clean, minimalistic favicon. This article quickly lists the steps to add a favicon to a Hugo website like this one.
 Create a favicon in an art package like Illustrator or Inkscape. Upload your image to Real Favicon Generator Extract the favicon package it creates to the /static/ directory which lives in the root of your HUGO site. Copy the given html and add it to your /layouts/partials/head.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>War | Coding a Card Game</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/war/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/war/</guid>
      <description>War Simulation in Python Game designer Greg Costikyan has observed that since there are no choices in the game, and all outcomes are random, it cannot be considered a game by some definitions. I chose to program this game because its complete random chance feature. It was an opportunity to practice python and writing recursive functions. The objective of the game is to win all cards. A 52-card deck is divided evenly among the players, giving each a down stack.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Data Types</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/r-data-types/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/r-data-types/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Truth is ever to be found in simplicity, and not in the multiplicity and confusion of things.&amp;rdquo;
Isaac Newton I approached R in the same way I would any language. I immediately delve into for-loops, conditional statements, user-defined functions, classes, and so on. I didn&amp;rsquo;t pay much attention to data types at first - assuming they&amp;rsquo;re not much different than what I&amp;rsquo;ve seen already. I found myself using dataframes and matricies often with low confidence and a lingering confusion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mathematics of Network Theory</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2018/network-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2018/network-theory/</guid>
      <description>Graphs may be represented in the form of a matrix. Main types of graphs that may be represented are:
 Simple Graph Multigraph Directed Graph Weighted Graph Bipartite Graph  Directed Graph Directed graphs are graphs that contain edges with direction. Vertices may have inward and outward edges.
Unlike adjacency matricies for simped graphs, adjacency matricies for directed graphs are non-symmetric. Elements of an adjacency matrix for a directed graph may be denoted as: $$A_{ij}$$ which represents an edge from vertex $j$ to $i$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lagrangian Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2017/gen-coord/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2017/gen-coord/</guid>
      <description>Generalized Coordinates and Conservation Laws From the Lagrangian Formulation of Theoretical Mechanics These are selected notes from a group of topics I find of particular interest. Although I assume some previous knowledge of classical mechanics from you, I still provide a brief overview of what the Lagrangian method is, where it comes from, how it relates to the more familiar Newtonian formulation, and how these beautiful laws of nature imply conserved quantities in everyday systems.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>