<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>articles - Eric Peña</title>
    <link>//ericpena.github.io/articles/index.xml</link>
    <description></description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 00:00:00 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    
        <atom:link href="//ericpena.github.io/articles/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cellular Automata Introduction</title>
      <link>//ericpena.github.io/articles/cellular_automata_intro.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//ericpena.github.io/articles/cellular_automata_intro.html</guid>
      <description>Motivation  &amp;ldquo;With four parameters I can fit an elephant, and with five I can make him wiggle his trunk.&amp;rdquo; &amp;ndash; John von Neumann
 Throughout history, science has aimed to understand and model the natural world as accurately as possible despite its inherent complexity. There are many phenomena in nature whose patterns and behavior seem somewhat unpredictable yet these resulting patterns appear highly structured and organized. Scientists and mathematicians have developed techniques (e.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Review of Complexity Book by Melanie Mitchell</title>
      <link>//ericpena.github.io/articles/mitchell.html</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>//ericpena.github.io/articles/mitchell.html</guid>
      <description>Part I: Introduction Providing the multifaceted story of how complex systems has evolved into what it is today is no easy feat. Dr. Melanie Mitchell not only gives a comprehensive historical tour of science and mathematics, she also provides foundational knowledge that any reader can carry to appreciate the essence of what it means for a system to be complex in the technical sense. Early on, she gives a clear definition of complex systems as an interdisciplinary field that studies how large networks of entities with no central controller can organize themselves and exhibit collective behavior given simple rules.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>