<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Complex Systems on Eric Peña</title>
    <link>https://ericpena.github.io/tags/complex-systems/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Complex Systems on Eric Peña</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ericpena.github.io/tags/complex-systems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Complexity – A Guided Tour Reflection</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/complexity-reflection-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2019/complexity-reflection-1/</guid>
      <description>Part I: Providing the multifaceted story of how complex systems has evolved into what it is today is no easy feat. Dr. Melanie Mitchell not only gives a comprehensive historical tour of science and mathematics, she also provides foundational knowledge that any reader can carry to appreciate the essence of what it means for a system to be complex in the technical sense. Early on, she gives a clear definition of complex systems as an interdisciplinary field that studies how large networks of entities with no central controller can organize themselves and exhibit collective behavior given simple rules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mathematics of Network Theory</title>
      <link>https://ericpena.github.io/2018/network-theory/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ericpena.github.io/2018/network-theory/</guid>
      <description>Graphs may be represented in the form of a matrix. Main types of graphs that may be represented are:
 Simple Graph Multigraph Directed Graph Weighted Graph Bipartite Graph  Directed Graph Directed graphs are graphs that contain edges with direction. Vertices may have inward and outward edges.
Unlike adjacency matricies for simped graphs, adjacency matricies for directed graphs are non-symmetric. Elements of an adjacency matrix for a directed graph may be denoted as: $$A_{ij}$$ which represents an edge from vertex $j$ to $i$.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>